Guide to the Allison Davis Papers 1932-1984
University of Chicago Library
- Series V: Research Files
  - Subseries 7: Intelligence Testing
    - Sub-subseries 3: Davis Tests
      - "Notes for Intelligence Test,", new test items, manuscripts, correspondence, notes, 1949 (Box 56, Folder 2)
      - "Notes for Intelligence Test,", plans and diagrams, sketches, notes, clippings, undated (Box 56, Folder 3)
      - "Notes for Intelligence Test,", classification test--common experience rural and urban, notes, undated (Box 56, Folder 4)
      - "Notes for Intelligence Test,", rhythm type problems, sketches, notes, note cards, clipping, undated (Box 56, Folder 5)
      - "Experimental Individual Intelligence Test," manuscript, tables, notes, undated (Box 56, Folder 6)
      - "Experimental Individual Intelligence Test,", item analysis, class and sex, manuscript, tables, undated (Box 56, Folder 7)
      - "Experimental Individual Intelligence Test,", Lab School sample, tables, 1951 (Box 56, Folder 8)
      - "Experimental Individual Intelligence Test,", Pearson Product Moment correlations, charts, tables, notes, 1950 (Box 56, Folder 9)
      - "Experimental Group Intelligence Test," manuscripts, outline, reprint, notes, 1948-1949 (Box 56, Folder 10)
      - "Experimental Group Intelligence Test," error group test analysis, tables, notes, 1949 (Box 56, Folder 11)
      - "Experimental Group Intelligence Test," group--item analysis, Tests A-E, correspondence, tables, notes, 1949 (Box 57, Folder 1)
      - "Experimental Group Intelligence Test," group--mean scores, tables, notes, 1949 (Box 57, Folder 2)
      - Other standardized tests, booklets, reprints, 1936-1942 (Box 57, Folder 3)
      - Other standardized tests, item analyses, tables, notes, 1946, "Notes for Intelligence Test," item analysis tables, 1947, SEE Box 87, Folders 3-5 "Experimental Individual Intelligence Test," Pearson Product Moment correlations, charts, tables, notes, 1950 SEE Box 87, Folder 6 "Experimental Group Intelligence Test," error group test analysis, tables, notes, 1949 SEE Box 87, Folder 7 "Experimental Group Intelligence Test," group--item analysis, Tests A-E, tables, 1949 SEE Box 87, Folder 8 Other standardized tests, tables, notes, booklets, reprints, 1936-1942, 1946, SEE Box 87, Folder 9 (Box 57, Folder 4)
  - Subseries 8: Young Adulthood Project
    - Sub-subseries 1: General
      - Notes, partial manuscripts, undated (Box 57, Folder 5-6)
      - Correspondence, memoranda, news release, 1960-1963 (Box 57, Folder 7-8)
      - "Achievement During Adolescence and Adulthood," manuscript, correspondence, 1963 (Box 57, Folder 9)
      - "Book Plan," manuscripts, notes, 1963-1966 (Box 57, Folder 10-11)
      - "Foreward," with Robert D. Hess, manuscript, undated (Box 57, Folder 12)
      - "The Future Education of Children from Low Socio-Economic Groups," manuscripts, notes, undated (Box 57, Folder 13)
      - "Identity in the Child and Adolescent," manuscript, undated (Box 57, Folder 14)
      - "Mental Health in Adolescence," with Robert D. Hess, proposal, 1955 (Box 57, Folder 15)
      - "Relationships between Achievement in High School, College and Occupation," with Robert D. Hess, manuscript, 1963 (Box 58, Folder 1-2)
      - "Relationships between Achievement in High School, College and Occupation," Cliques and constellations, "Making a Play," "The Big Wheel," "The Hellers," "Center Stage," manuscripts, undated (Box 58, Folder 3-4)
      - "Relationships between Achievement in High School, College and Occupation,""The Outline to the Appendix," Appendices, manuscripts, undated (Box 58, Folder 5-6)
      - "Social and Emotional Development within Adolescence," manuscript, notes, undated (Box 58, Folder 7)
      - "The Social Life of Young Adults," partial manuscript, undated (Box 58, Folder 8)
      - "Society, the School, and the Culturally Deprived Student," partial manuscript, undated (Box 58, Folder 9)
      - "Summary of Address to Be Given at Pennsylvania State University to the Graduate School," manuscripts, notes, 1958 (Box 58, Folder 10)
      - Bar-On, Mordechai, "Education Processes in the Israel Defence Forces," manuscript, 1966 (Box 58, Folder 11)
      - Bidwell, Charles E. and Rebecca S. Vreeland, "College Education and Moral Orientations," manuscript, 1962 (Box 58, Folder 12)
      - Bloom, Benjamin S., "Early Learning in the Home," manuscript, 1965 (Box 58, Folder 13)
      - Fielder, Marie, "The School as a Social System," dissertation abstract, 1953 (Box 58, Folder 14)
      - Forman, Jack, "Variables to Be Considered at Some Length," manuscript, 1962 (Box 58, Folder 15)
      - Granetz, Ruth, "Self Perception as Related to Social Structure in Early Adulthood," dissertation proposal, 1961 (Box 58, Folder 16)
      - Hale, B. J., "The Occupational Life of Married and Single Males," manuscript, outline, memorandum, 1962 (Box 59, Folder 1)
      - Hale, B. J., "The Transition from Adolescence to Young Adulthood," manuscripts, correspondence, 1962 (Box 59, Folder 2)
      - Handel, Gerald, "Sociological Aspects of Parenthood," manuscript, 1968 (Box 59, Folder 3)
      - Hess, Robert D., "Maternal Behavior and the Development of Reading Readiness in Urban Negro Children," "Cognitive Elements in Maternal Behavior," with Virginia C. Shipman, "Maternal Language Styles and Their Implications for Children's Cognitive Development," with Ellis G. Olim and Virginia C. Shipman, manuscripts, ca. 1965 (Box 59, Folder 4)
      - Katzin, Betty, "The Single Women," "Two Wives," manuscripts, notes, 1962 (Box 59, Folder 5)
      - National Opinion Research Center, "A Brush-Up on Interviewing Technique," manuscript, 1957 (Box 59, Folder 6)
      - National Scholarship Service and Fund for Negro Students, "Text of Speeches Delivered at NSSFNS Dinner in Chicago," pamphlet, 1959 (Box 59, Folder 7)
      - Nawas, M. Mike and Judy Schaefer, "The Thematic Apperception Technique and Its Application to the Population of the Young Adulthood Project," manuscript, undated (Box 59, Folder 8)
      - Puttkammer, Charles, "Negroes in the Ivy League," manuscript, 1961-1962 (Box 59, Folder 9)
      - Schaefer, Judy, "The Fantasy of Single and Married Males," manuscript, notes, 1962 (Box 59, Folder 10)
      - Starr Commonwealth for Boys and the Michigan Council for Family Relations, "Invitational Conference on Youth in Tomorrow's Culture," pamphlet, undated (Box 59, Folder 11)
      - Wechsler, David, Wechsler Intelligence Scale for Children, manual, 1949 (Box 60, Folder 1)
      - Unidentified, manuscript, undated (Box 60, Folder 2)
      - Reprints, 1933-1962 (Box 60, Folder 3)
    - Sub-subseries 2: Research Memoranda
      - Nature of the 1952 sample, undated (Box 60, Folder 4)
      - Questionnaires, Calumet High School, 1952, 1959 (Box 60, Folder 5)
      - Summary of plans of 5270 high school and vocational school graduates, 1954 (Box 60, Folder 6)
      - Tables of intercorrelations by variable, 1961 (Box 60, Folder 7)
      - Memo #1, Dorothy Maddi, 1960 (Box 60, Folder 8)
      - Memo #2, 8, 12, 13, 26, statistical analyses, Ruth Granetz, 1960-1961 (Box 60, Folder 9)
      - Memo #3, 16, Thematic Apperception Tests, Judy Schaefer, 1961 (Box 60, Folder 10)
      - Memo #4, 17, women, Betty Katzin, 1961 (Box 60, Folder 11)
      - Memo #5, Robert Hess, 1961 (Box 60, Folder 12)
      - Memo #6, Jerry Gerasimo, 1961 (Box 60, Folder 13)
      - Memo #7, men, Hale, 1961 (Box 60, Folder 14)
      - Memo #9, Nancy Gordon, 1961 (Box 60, Folder 15)
      - Memo #10, 21, Thematic Apperception Tests, M. Mike Nawas, 1961 (Box 60, Folder 16)
      - Memo #11, Robert Hess, 1961 (Box 60, Folder 17)
      - Memo #15, high school, Dorothy Maddi, 1961 (Box 60, Folder 18)
      - Memo #19, Viator, 1961 (Box 60, Folder 19)
      - Memo #20, Jack Foreman, 1961 (Box 60, Folder 20)
      - Memo #22, Jack Foreman, 1961 (Box 60, Folder 21)
      - Memo #23, Jack Foreman, 1961 (Box 60, Folder 22)
      - Memo #24, Jack Foreman, notes, undated (Box 60, Folder 23)
      - Memo #27, Helen McMahan, 1961 (Box 60, Folder 24)
      - Memo #28, Jack Foreman, 1961 (Box 60, Folder 25)
      - Memo #29, Judy Schaefer, 1961 (Box 60, Folder 26)
      - Memo #30, Allison Davis, 1961 (Box 60, Folder 27)
      - Memo #31, Jack Foreman, 1961 (Box 60, Folder 28)
      - Memo #34, Jack Foreman, undated (Box 60, Folder 29)
    - Sub-subseries 3: Interview Data
      - Kewpies, interviewed by Ruth Granetz and Elizabeth Davis, Thematic Apperception Test, TAT, transcripts, notes, 1959 (Box 61, Folder 1)
      - Negro Cases, Dorothy Holmes, interviewed by Betty Rodgers, transcript, chart, 1959 (Box 61, Folder 2)
      - Negro Cases, Shyrlie Nickerson Johnson, interviewed by Betty Rodgers, TAT, transcript, notes, undated (Box 61, Folder 3)
      - Negro Cases, Rochelle Rhodes Massingale, interviewed by Betty Rodgers, TAT, transcript, notes, 1959 (Box 61, Folder 4)
      - Negro Cases, Barbara Purnell, interviewed by Betty Rodgers, TAT, transcripts, questionnaires, charts, notes, 1952-1959 (Box 61, Folder 5-6)
      - Negro Cases, Elinor Tyler Vaughn, interviewed by Elizabeth Davis, transcript, undated (Box 61, Folder 7)
      - Negro Cases, Kay Slater Williams, interviewed by Betty Rodgers, TAT, transcript, notes, undated (Box 61, Folder 8)
      - Benson, Mark, interviewed by Betty Katzin, memoranda, 1962 (Box 61, Folder 9)
      - Borring, Allen, interviewed by Judy Schaefer, TAT, problem solving analyses, 1954 (Box 61, Folder 10)
      - Gialamas, James, interviewed by Jerry Gerasimo, transcript, notes, 1959 (Box 61, Folder 11)
      - Hecht, Alfred, interviewed by Jerry Gerasimo, transcript, notes, 1959 (Box 61, Folder 12)
      - Hempel, Joan, unidentified interviewer, notes, 1954 (Box 61, Folder 13)
      - Hodsdon, Joan Ricketts, reply form, 1959 (Box 61, Folder 14)
      - Irwin, Doris [Dora Dixon], interviewed by Judy Schaefer, transcript, notes, 1954 (Box 61, Folder 15)
      - Jacobs, Josephine Pondelicek, interviewed by Ruth Granetz, TAT, transcripts, notes, 1959 (Box 62, Folder 1)
      - Jensen, Jeanne, unidentified interviewer, notes, 1954 (Box 62, Folder 2)
      - Johnson, Beverly Kae, interviewed by Ruth Granetz, transcript, notes, 1959 (Box 62, Folder 3)
      - Ketchum, Margaret Bergmann, interviewed by Ruth Granetz, transcripts, excerpts, notes, 1958-1959 (Box 62, Folder 4)
      - Law, Diane, interviewed by Ruth Granetz, TAT, transcript, notes, 1959 (Box 62, Folder 5)
      - Lecos, James, interviewed by Jerry Gerasimo, transcript, notes, undated (Box 62, Folder 6)
      - Lisle, Thomas V., interviewed by Jerry Gerasimo, transcript, notes, 1959 (Box 62, Folder 7)
      - Mayer, Don V., interviewed by Jerry Gerasimo, TAT, transcripts, notes, 1959 (Box 62, Folder 8)
      - Palm, Janice, interviewed by Ruth Granetz, transcript, notes, 1959 (Box 62, Folder 9)
      - Richard, Lois Stanton, interviewed by Ruth Granetz, transcript, excerpts, notes, 1959 (Box 62, Folder 10)
      - Ruddick, Wayne, interviewed by Jerry Gerasimo, transcript, notes, 1959 (Box 62, Folder 11)
      - Serving, John, unidentified interviewer, notes, 1954 (Box 62, Folder 12)
      - Smedberg, Merle, interviewed by Elizabeth Davis, TAT, transcripts, notes, 1954, ca. 1962 (Box 62, Folder 13)
      - Stienz, Grace Schwantes, interviewed by Ruth Granetz, notes, 1959 (Box 62, Folder 14)
      - Wiersema, Grace, interviewed by Ruth Granetz, TAT, transcript, excerpts, notes, 1959 (Box 62, Folder 15)
      - Wolcott, Ethel Humecke, interviewed by Ruth Granetz, transcript, notes, 1959 (Box 62, Folder 16)
- Series VI: Writings
  This series brings together a broad spectrum of Davis's professional and non-professional writing, including three book-length efforts undertaken towards the end of his career.
  Though neither work seems to have been published, Davis apparently considered both To Seize Life and Sexual Vitality to be extensions of his work on ego development and maintenance, but intended for more popular audiences. The materials are very closely related and, in fact, not easily partitioned. They incorporate much of the same content, but in rather different forms and guises. It should likewise be noted that Davis reworked this material many, many times, and while relatively complete versions of the works are included here, one will also find a substantial amount of partial manuscripts and notes. Similarly, several versions of Leadership, Love, and Aggression, as well as materials pertaining to the development of each chapter, are included here.
  The Non-Fiction section is not intended to be inclusive of Davis's work. Rather, it reflects those manuscripts and reprints which he had himself arranged together. These works, published and unpublished, cover an expansive period from 1933 to 1973. Lectures, where distinguishable from Non-Fiction, includes public addresses and speeches delivered between 1949 and 1973.
  Finally, a brief Fiction section presents notes and manuscripts for several literary works. It appears that Davis returned to this material throughout his lifetime, as indicated by dates ranging from 1934 to 1983.
  - Subseries 1: To Seize Life
    - Interview data, D. F. Rogers, TAT., notes, undated (Box 62, Folder 17)
    - Interview data, TAT responses, undated (Box 62, Folder 18)
    - Commencement Address, University of Chicago, partial manuscript, 1976 (Box 62, Folder 19)
    - "Facing Fear," manuscript, undated (Box 62, Folder 20)
    - "Seize Life (While You Can)," "How to Enjoy Life," manuscripts, undated (Box 62, Folder 21)
    - To Seize Life, manuscripts, notes, ca. 1967 (Box 63, Folder 1-5)
    - To Seize Life, manuscripts, ca. 1967 (Box 64, Folder 1-7)
    - To Seize Life, book-length manuscripts, notes, ca. 1972-1979 (Box 65, Folder 1-3)
    - To Seize Life, introduction, manuscripts, undated (Box 65, Folder 4)
    - To Seize Life, Section I, Hope, manuscripts, notes, undated (Box 65, Folder 5)
    - To Seize Life, Section II, Sexual Vitality, manuscripts, notes, undated (Box 65, Folder 6)
    - To Seize Life, Section IV, Self-Renewal, manuscripts, notes, undated (Box 65, Folder 7)
  - Subseries 2: Sexual Vitality
    - Correspondence, 1975 (Box 65, Folder 8)
    - Notes, notebooks, partial manuscripts, clippings, 1970-1975 (Box 65, Folder 9-11)
    - Notes, notebooks, 1970-1975 (Box 66, Folder 1-3)
    - Notes, sex and anger, undated (Box 66, Folder 4)
    - "The Age of Anger--and Fear," partial manuscript, undated (Box 66, Folder 5)
    - "The Chances for Mixed Marriage," manuscripts, notes, 1975 (Box 66, Folder 6)
    - "Memo: Yes, Happy Sex Requires More than Sexual Vitality," "How to Save Your Marriage," manuscripts, undated (Box 66, Folder 7)
    - Bell, Alan P., "Black Sexuality," manuscript, 1968 (Box 67, Folder 1)
    - Samuels, Ruth S., "Sex and Power in a New Orleans Black Community," manuscript, 1974 (Box 67, Folder 2)
    - Reprints, 1953-1977 (Box 67, Folder 3)
    - Sexual Vitality, book-length manuscript, undated (Box 67, Folder 4-5)
    - Sexual Vitality, Part One, "Sexual Vitality and Fertility," partial manuscript, undated (Box 67, Folder 6)
    - Sexual Vitality, Part Two, "What Kills Sexual Vitality," manuscripts, notes, 1974-1975 (Box 67, Folder 7)
    - Black Sexual Vitality, book-length manuscript, undated (Box 67, Folder 8-10)
    - Black Sexual Vitality, "The Subject," introductory materials, manuscripts, notes, undated (Box 67, Folder 11)
    - Black Sexual Vitality, conclusion, partial manuscript, notes, undated (Box 67, Folder 12)
    - Black Sexual Vitality, Part I, "Black Sexual Vitality," manuscripts, notes, 1974-1975 (Box 68, Folder 1-4)
    - Black Sexual Vitality, Part II, "What's Killing Cock Robin?," manuscripts, notes, 1975 (Box 68, Folder 5)
    - Black Sexual Vitality, Part III, "White-Black Sexual Unions," manuscripts, notes, 1974-1975 (Box 68, Folder 6-7)
  - Subseries 3: Leadership, Love, and Aggression
    - Bibliographies, undated (Box 68, Folder 8)
    - Notes for Studs Terkel interview, undated (Box 68, Folder 9)
    - "Anger, Initiative, and Leadership," manuscript, undated (Box 68, Folder 10)
    - "Leadership and Aggression," manuscript, undated (Box 68, Folder 11)
    - Leadership and Aggression, book-length manuscripts, excerpts, notes, undated (Box 69, Folder 1-4)
    - Leadership, Love, and Aggression, five book-length manuscripts, editorial notes, 1983 (Box 69, Folder 5-11)
    - Leadership, Love, and Aggression, five book-length manuscripts, 1983, Artwork for front matter, 1982, SEE Box 87, Folder 10 (Box 70, Folder 1-5)
    - Galley proofs, notes, correspondence, 1983 (Box 70, Folder 6-13)
    - "Statement for Jacket of Leadership, Love, and Aggression," manuscript, notes, undated (Box 71, Folder 1)
    - "Transformations of Aggression," manuscripts, notes, undated (Box 71, Folder 2)
    - Frederick Douglass materials, correspondence, 1980-1981 (Box 71, Folder 3)
    - Frederick Douglass materials, partial manuscripts, notes, 1979-1980 (Box 71, Folder 4-8)
    - Frederick Douglass materials, Mark W. Dean, notes, undated (Box 71, Folder 9)
    - Frederick Douglass materials, "Douglass, the Lion," manuscripts, notes, undated (Box 72, Folder 1-5)
    - Frederick Douglass materials, "Douglass, the Lion," editorial notes, correspondence, undated (Box 72, Folder 6)
    - W. E. B. Du Bois materials, correspondence, 1973-1981 (Box 72, Folder 7)
    - W. E. B. Du Bois materials, "Anger and Identity," partial manuscript, notes, undated (Box 72, Folder 8)
    - W. E. B. Du Bois materials, "Anger as a Defense of the Ego," manuscripts, notes, undated (Box 72, Folder 9)
    - W. E. B. Du Bois materials, "Du Bois and the Problem of the Black Masses," manuscripts, notes, 1974-1977 (Box 72, Folder 10-11)
    - W. E. B. Du Bois materials, "Du Bois in Perspective," manuscript, notes, undated (Box 72, Folder 12)
    - W. E. B. Du Bois materials, "Du Bois, the Non-Pareil," manuscripts, notes, undated (Box 73, Folder 1-2)
    - W. E. B. Du Bois materials, "Du Bois: Scholar, Leader, and Radical," partial manuscript, undated (Box 73, Folder 3)
    - W. E. B. Du Bois materials, "The Intellectual as Leader: the Lonely Warrior," manuscripts, notes, undated (Box 73, Folder 4-7)
    - W. E. B. Du Bois materials, Francis Broderick, "W. E. B. Du Bois: A Late Historical View," manuscript, 1972 (Box 74, Folder 1)
    - W. E. B. Du Bois materials, Mark W. Dean, "Du Bois' Personality," manuscript, correspondence, bibliographies, notes, note cards, 1979 (Box 74, Folder 2-3)
    - W. E. B. Du Bois materials, Martin Kilson, "Black Social Classes and Intergenerational Poverty," reprint, undated (Box 74, Folder 4)
    - Richard Wright materials, correspondence, notes, clippings, 1975-1977 (Box 74, Folder 5)
    - Richard Wright materials, "The Origins of Richard Wright's Anger," previously "Richard Wright: a Sociological and Psychological Study of the Creator of Native Son," presented at University of Iowa, manuscripts, notes, 1977 (Box 74, Folder 6-7)
    - Richard Wright materials, "Mightier Than the Sword," manuscripts, notes, undated (Box 75, Folder 1-2)
    - Richard Wright materials, Charles T. Davis, "Black Boy as Art," manuscript, undated (Box 75, Folder 3)
    - Martin Luther King, Jr. materials, correspondence, notes, undated (Box 75, Folder 4-6)
    - Martin Luther King, Jr. materials, media interviews, transcripts, clippings, 1976-1979 (Box 75, Folder 7)
    - Martin Luther King, Jr. materials, "Black Leader's Handling of Their Own Anger," Solomon Fuller Lecture, manuscript, undated (Box 75, Folder 8)
    - Martin Luther King, Jr. materials, "A Proposal for a Study of the Psychical Development of Martin Luther King, Jr.," manuscripts, notes, 1979-1982 (Box 75, Folder 9-10)
    - Martin Luther King, Jr. materials, "Amazing Love," manuscripts, notes, undated (Box 75, Folder 11-13)
    - Martin Luther King, Jr. materials, "Amazing Love," undated (Box 76, Folder 1-3)
    - Dean, Mark W., notes, note cards, undated (Box 76, Folder 4-7)
    - Dean, Mark W., "General Armstrong," manuscript, 1979 (Box 76, Folder 8)
    - Dean, Mark W., Theodore Roosevelt, research materials, notes, undated (Box 76, Folder 9)
    - Dean, Mark W., Booker T. Washington, research materials, interviews, notes, 1974 (Box 76, Folder 10)
    - Dean, Mark W., Booker T. Washington, "Black Leadership," manuscript, notes, undated (Box 76, Folder 11)
    - Ellison, Ralph, "Juneteenth," reprint, undated (Box 76, Folder 12)
    - Johnson, Kenneth R., "The Vocabulary of Race," manuscript, correspondence, 1970 (Box 76, Folder 13)
    - Ward, Adelaide, "The Identity Crisis of Malcolm X," student paper, undated (Box 76, Folder 14)
  - Subseries 4: Articles
    - "The Able among the Socially Disadvantaged," manuscripts, 1968 (Box 76, Folder 15)
    - "Achievement During Adolescence and Adulthood," manuscripts, undated (Box 76, Folder 16)
    - "Adolescent Psychology: Social and Emotional Development Within Adolescence," manuscripts, undated (Box 77, Folder 1)
    - "American Status Systems and the Socialization of the Child," reprint, manuscript, notes, 1941 (Box 77, Folder 2)
    - "Anger and Leadership," manuscripts, undated (Box 77, Folder 3)
    - "Anger, Initiative, and Leadership," manuscript, undated (Box 77, Folder 4)
    - "Applied Research Upon Group and Individual Therapy for Delinquents," manuscript, 1948 (Box 77, Folder 5)
    - "Audio-Visual Aids in Intercultural Education," manuscript, undated (Box 77, Folder 6)
    - "Basic Concepts in the Education of Ethnic and Lowerclass Groups," manuscript, notes, 1945 (Box 77, Folder 7)
    - "The Basic Principle if Child Rearing," partial manuscript, undated (Box 77, Folder 8)
    - "Black Leadership and Anger," reprints, manuscript, notes, 1973 (Box 77, Folder 9)
    - "Caste, Economy, and Violence," reprint, 1945 (Box 77, Folder 10)
    - "Changing Patterns of Socialization in the Family," manuscript, reprint, correspondence, 1964 (Box 77, Folder 11)
    - "Changing the Culture of the Disadvantaged Student," manuscript, undated (Box 77, Folder 12)
    - "Child Training and Social Class," reprint, manuscripts, notes, undated (Box 77, Folder 13)
    - "Children as the Basic Human Resources of the United States in the Building of an Expanding Nation, Society, and Economy," manuscripts, notes, undated (Box 77, Folder 14)
    - "Compensatory Education fro Cultural Deprivation," with Benjamin S. Bloom and Robert Hess, manuscripts, 1964 (Box 77, Folder 15)
    - "A Constructive Program for ADC," manuscript, undated (Box 77, Folder 16)
    - "Cultural Factors in Remediation," manuscripts, reprints, notes, 1965 (Box 77, Folder 17)
    - "The Culture of the Slum," manuscript, undated (Box 77, Folder 18)
    - "Developing an Improved Primary Curriculum," reprint, 1949 (Box 77, Folder 19)
    - "Developmental Relationships Between the Parental Family and the New Family," (Box 77, Folder 20)
    - "The Distribution of the Blood Groups and Its Bearing on the Concept of Race," manuscripts, reprint, notes, 1933-1935 (Box 78, Folder 1)
    - "The Educability of the Children of the Poor," manuscripts, undated (Box 78, Folder 2)
    - "The Education of Socially Disadvantaged Children," manuscript, undated (Box 78, Folder 3)
    - "Educational Mobilization and the Development of the Full Potential of the United States," manuscripts, undated (Box 78, Folder 4)
    - "Ego-Development in Adolescence," introduction, manuscript, outline, 1966 (Box 78, Folder 5)
    - "The Ego and Status Anxiety," reprints, manuscripts, notes, 1955-1956 (Box 78, Folder 6)
    - "The Future Education of Children From Low Socio-Economic Groups," manuscripts, undated (Box 79, Folder 1)
    - "How Your Child Gets His Personality," manuscripts, notes, undated (Box 79, Folder 2)
    - "Identity in the Child and Adolescent," manuscript, notes, undated (Box 79, Folder 3)